RG 092, Connecticut State Dental Commission
Connecticut State Library
Dental Commission records
1893-1950
Connecticut State Library
Connecticut State Dental Commission
4 cubic feet
Established in 1893, the Connecticut Dental Commission regulates the practice of dentistry and dental hygiene including examining and licensing of dentists and dental hygienists. Originally an independent entity, the Commission became part of the Department of Public Health in 1979.
RG092
T002767
Historical Note
Established in 1893, the Connecticut Dental Commission regulates the practice of dentistry and dental hygiene including examining and licensing of dentists and dental hygienists. Originally an independent entity, the Commission became part of the Department of Public Health in 1979.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of applications for licenses, lists of dentists in Connecticut, meeting minutes, and photographs. The collection also includes the license of Dr. Evangeline Roberts Jones, the first woman in the United States to practice dentistry full-time to support herself and her family.
Related Material
Index Terms
Organizations:
Connecticut State Dental Commission
Occupations:
Dentists
Subjects:
Connecticut State Dental Commission -- Records and correspondence; Dentists -- Connecticut; Dentists -- Licenses -- Connecticut
Document Types:
Application forms; Bills (legislative records); Lists; Minutes; Photographs
Restrictions on Access
See the policy.
Container List
- Records, 1893-1950
  - 1. Applications, 1893-1950
    Original applications for the licensing of dentists and dental hygienists. Includes applications which were not approved.
    For the most part, the applications are in bound volumes. Some volumes contain several parts. Bound volumes arranged chronologically, then alphabetically within volume.
    - Applications not bound, 1911-1914 (Box Box 1)
    - Applications of those who did not pass, 1931-1940 (Box Box 1)
    - Duplicates of Volume 4, 1906-1910; 3 folders (Box Box 1)
      Volume 4 is Item 10.
    - Applications, 1893; 1 volume (Box Item 2)
    - Aplications for registration, 1893-1901; 1 volume (Box Item 4 (Vol. 1))
    - Duplicates, 1893 January 23 - 1900 June 1; 1 volume (Box Item 5 (Vol. 1B))
    - Applications for license, 1893-1900; 1 volume (Box Item 6 (Vol. 2))
    - Applications for license, 1900 June 1 - 1901 July 1; 1 volume (Box Item 7 (Vol. 2A))
    - Applications for registration, 1893 November-December; 1 volume (Box Item 8 (Vol. 2B))
    - Applications for License, 1901-1905; 1 volume (Box Item 9 (Vol. 3))
    - Applications for license, 1906-1910; 1 volume (Box Item 10 (Vol. 4))
    - Application for license, 1911-1915; 1 volume (Box Item 11 (Vol. 5))
    - Application for license, 1916-1920; 1 volume (Box Item 12 (Vol. 6))
    - Application for license, dentists, 1921-1930; 1 volume (Box Item 13 (Vol. 7))
    - Application for license, hygienists, 1921-1930; 1 volume (Box Item 14 (Vol. 8))
    - Unlicensed, hygienists and dentists, 1915-1928; 1 volume (Box Item 15 (Vol. 9))
    - Application for license, dentists, A-K, 1931-1940; 1 volume (Box Item 16 (Vol. 10 Part 1))
    - Apploication for license, dentists, L-Z, 1931-1940; 1 volume (Box Item 17 (Vol. 10 Part 2))
    - Application for license, hygienists, 1931-1940; 1 volume (Box Item 18 (Vol. 11))
    - Application for license, dentists, A-Z, 1941-1948; 1 volume (Box Item 19 (Vol. 12))
    - Application for license, hygienists, 1941-1950; 1 volume (Box Item 20 (Vol. 13))
  - 2. List of dentists in Connecticut, 1901; 1 volume (Box Item 3)
    The list was compiled by the postmasters at the request of the dental commissioner.
    Postmaster's lists of dentists residing in each town in the state.
  - 3. Records of the Dental Commissioners of Connecticut, 1893-1901 (Box Box 21)
    Includes copies of legislation pertaining to the establishment of the commission, minutes of meetings, and copies of examinations.
  - 4. Registration numbers and a list of those unregistered, circa 1900 (Box Box 21)
  - 5. Sample forms, circa 1900 (Box Box 21)
  - 6. Photographs, 1941-1950 (Box Box 22)
    Photographs taken from applications of dentists and dental hygienists.